All
right, good morning. I'm Dan Margulies, I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer
while he's away. Today's the third of טבת, Tevet, it's the last
day of חנוכה, Chanukah, and it's January 1st, so it explains why
some people are a little bit more tired today than usual.
So we're going to pick up with right towards the top of
ט"ז עמוד א' Ted-Zayin Amud Aleph with a little bit of background
going back to what we saw yesterday, which is that we've at
least somewhat transitioned from the discussion of the first פטור ptur for
a שואל, shoel, which is the פטור ptur of בעליו עמו, baalav
imo, that the owner of whatever object was borrowed has been hired
or asked to work alongside the borrower, and that provides an exemption.
And then the second one is מתה מחמת מלאכה, meitah machmat melachah,
that the animal or the object dies or is broken from normal
use.
So some of the explanations given for why מתה מחמת מלאכה meitah
machmat melachah is a פטור, ptur, basically two possibilities. Either one is
that actually the משאיל, mashil, the one who lent the object or
the animal, is actually it's a certain level of פשיעה pshia on
his part. Because think about what happened if the animal can't sustain
a normal amount of work, well then you shouldn't have lent it
out in the first place. So it's really the owner's liability for
having falsely guaranteed the animal or the object to be able to
withstand that sort of use. The second possibility is just a sort
of normal wear and tear. And normal wear and tear is something
that's totally to be expected on the part of the owner, that
if you lend something out to be used, that it's going to
have that level of damage. And if it dies or if it's
broken, sort of that was to be expected.
To answer your question yesterday, David, I think
if I'm remembering correctly, you had a question
about—I was thinking about it when I walked over here. If it
comes back to me
or
remind me again at the end. Okay, so we had seen the
case of רב Rav פוסק paskening the case of the axe. We
saw that רב Rav at first seemed to פוסק pasken לפנים משורת
הדין. lifnim mishurat hadin. רב כהנא Rav Kahana and רב אסי Rav
Assi had countered, דינא הכי? dina hachi? And it seems like the
הלכה halachah follows them, in fact, that in the case where the
person had lent an axe and the axe broke, the הלכה halachah
as quoted by רש"י Rashi based on בבא קמא Bava Kamma should
be really that the שואל shoel is only liable to pay
even if it wasn't מתה מחמת מלאכה, meitah machmat melachah, even if
it was a negligent use, then it has to be not the
full value of the axe but only partial value because we say
בעלים מטפלים בנבילה, bealim metaplim bineveilah, that the owner can keep the
broken axe and that was why what רב Rav said seemed to
not make so much sense. Now we'll continue on the third line
of ט"ז עמוד א'. Tez-Zayin Amud Aleph. ההוא גברא דשאל דולא מחבריה,
hahu gavra dshail dula mechavrei, the person borrowed a bucket from his
friend. תבר, Toitbar, it broke. אתא לקמיה דרב פפא, Ata lekamei dRav
Pappa, he comes before רב פפא. Rav Pappa. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
אייתי סהדי דלא שינית בה, ayiti sahadi dlo shinit bah, so bring
witnesses that you didn't change something. That's the same principle we saw
so far with רבא Rava and רב. Rav. ואיפטר, Veiftar, and you'll
be exempted. And so that was what רב פפא Rav Pappa told
him. That is, we can apply the principle of מתה מחמת מלאכה
meitah machmat melachah for inanimate objects, but interestingly enough, the burden of
proof lies on the שואל shoel to have to guarantee the proof
that the item was not used in a negligent fashion. Because think
about it, if something breaks, my first guess is going to be
that it's negligence, especially with a שואל shoel who has a very
high level of liability. Only after he's able to prove, then that's
why he would be exempt. Now I remember David's question and it
makes a lot of sense. The question is how come the שואל
shoel can't just exempt himself with a שבועה? shvua? רב פפא Rav
Pappa just says bring witnesses, bring witnesses. So very often in any
kind of שומרים shomrim case, you would assume the שומר shomer can
take שבועת השומרים. shvuat hashomrim. שבועה שלא פשעתי, Shvua shelo pashaya, שבועה
שלא שלחתי בו יד, shvua shelo shalakh bo yad, and that's what
many of the ראשונים Rishonim say is yes, he actually could take
the שבועה. shvua. It's just these cases incidentally there was no option
to bring witnesses or witnesses are the first option but the שבועה
shvua can get you out of it if there were no witnesses,
things like that. But actually there is one opinion in the ראשונים
Rishonim that gets rejected that's quoted by the ריטב"א Ritva that maybe
a שואל shoel is not the same as other kinds of שומרים
shomrim because a שואל shoel maybe would not be able to take
שבועת השומרים. shvuat hashomrim. So that was David's question yesterday, really getting
into the question of how different is שואל shoel from other שומרים.
shomrim. Maybe the שואל shoel has such a high level of liability
that there is no שבועת השומרים shvuat hashomrim that he could take
in order to exempt himself. That's a possibility.
So the old opinion is he's not allowed to take it?
No, so maybe the reason, so most of the ראשונים Rishonim think
a שואל shoel could take a שבועה, shvua, it's just that these
cases happen
to...
Okay. So now as Charlie posted on Facebook, his favorite case in
the גמרא, Gemara, ההוא גברא דשאל שונרא מחבריה, hahu gavra disha'al shunra
michavreih, someone borrowed a cat from his friend. Now why would you
borrow a cat? This is in the days before PetSmart, a cat
is a working animal.
The cat has to eat the mice. Not goats, usually cats can't
attack a goat unless it's like a mountain lion or something, but
a cat could attack mice.
So okay. So here the cat is going to be catching mice.
Ah, but what happens? This is kind of humorous: חברו עליה עכברי
וקטלוה. chavru aleih achbarei vekatluha.
So the the mice ganged up on the cat.
It's like Tom and Jerry.
It's like Tom and Jerry. But so there's a whole there's a
mouse infestation to the point where there are so many mice that
the mice can overpower one cat. יתיב רב אשי וקמיבעיא ליה כי
האי גוונא מאי. yativ Rav Ashi vekamibaia leih ki hai gavna mai.
So the students asked from רב אשי: Rav Ashi: so how would
you פסקן paskin in such a case? Does that count as מתה
מחמת מלאכה? meta machamat melacha? That is, the cat was trying to
catch the mice, but maybe the mice there were too many mice,
so maybe the שואל shoel was a פושע poushea in that the
terms of the agreement, he really needed multiple cats perhaps in order
to keep this infestation down or something like that. So כי מתה
מחמת מלאכה דמי או לא? ki meta machamat melacha dami o lo?
Is that like מתה מחמת מלאכה? meta machamat melacha? אמר ליה רב
מרדכי לרב אשי. amar leih Rav Mordechai le-Rav Ashi. So רב מרדכי
Rav Mordechai answered for רב אשי, Rav Ashi, interestingly who is giving
the שיעור? shiur? It's not so clear.
הכי אמר אבימי מהגרוניא משמיה דרבא. hachi amar Avimi mehagronya mishmeih de-Rava.
This is what אבימי Avimi said from הגרוניא Agronya who was quoting
רבא: Rava: גברא דנשי קטלוה. gavra denashei katluha. It's a little bit
of a sexist idiom, but we can unpack it a little bit.
גברא דנשי קטלוה, gavra denashei katluha, a man who was killed by
women,
לא דינא ולא דיינא. lo dina velo dayana. Something like that, it's
a kind of a powerful phrase. The idea here so far in
the case of this case seems to be, in especially in a
time where violent attacks were primarily being based on brute strength, if
there was a man who was overpowered by woman and killed by
her, you would imagine that that would be such a rare case
that it would be difficult in order to convince people that that
had happened. So here too, the claim is that the cat, the
mouse, the mice overpowering the cat is something so extreme and so
out of the ordinary that that falls into the normal category of
מתה מחמת מלאכה, meta machamat melacha, it's not something that the שואל
shoel would have been liable for. We're going to see in a
second actually a different interpretation of this line which still somewhat sexist
but certainly a different a different term. איכא דאמרי הכי אכל עכברי
טובא וחביל ומית. ika de-amri hachi achal achbarei tuva vechavil umit. So
there's a different version of the case: what was the case? Maybe
the cat ate, overstuffed itself with too many mice. It ate too
many mice and died. That so that could happen as well. יתיב
רב אשי וקא מעיין בה כהאי גוונא מאי. yativ Rav Ashi veka
maayan bah ki hai gavna mai. So and רב אשי Rav Ashi
was studying the case like this case and they and asked כהאי
גוונא מאי, ki hai gavna mai, right? אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב
אשי. amar leih Rav Mordechai le-Rav Ashi.
So רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai said back to רב אשי: Rav Ashi:
הכי אמר אבימי מהגרוניא גברא דנשי קטלוה. hachi amar Avimi mehagronya gavra
denashei katluha. So he says now in this case, the phrase, a
man who was killed by women. But if you look in רש''י,
Rashi, what does רש''י Rashi say here?
דנשי קטלוה, denashei katluha, בעל בעילות הרבה ומת, ba'al be'ilot harbeh umet,
that the man in in the analogy, in a case of the
cat who overstuffed itself with mice, is similar case where a man
was overly proclivious and was was in some way weakened or or
died from some sort of result of his escapades in that way.
So thinking about this turn of phrase in that way, a little
bit different, hard to unpack, certainly something to chew on. אמר רבא.
amar Rava. Yeah. Yeah, sure.
First question, who is
אבימי מהגרוניא?
Avimi mehagronya? אבימי Avimi is one of the late אמוראים Amoraim as
far as I remember. I don't know so much about him. You
could Google him and find out more.
Okay. Second, not direct directly, when did חתול chatul become שונרא? shunra?
Because שונרא shunra is the Aramaic word.
Right, but most in most languages that I'm aware of, the word
for cat is very similar to חתול chatul like cat or gato
in Spanish for instance. And שונרא, shunra, which is very closely related
to Hebrew, has a completely different word.
So I don't know where it comes from, one word might come
from Persian and one word could come from Greek or something, you
know I don't know. Cats were first domesticated in Egypt and then
they spread from there, so I don't know all the history of
it. Something to look into. You're the cat expert, so you have
that's your job.
Okay. אמר רבא האי מאן דבעי למישאל מידי מחבריה בלי שאל. amar
Rava hai man deba'ei lemish'al midi michavreih beli she'al. What if somebody
wants to to borrow something in a very efficient way? Someone wants
to borrow something and never have a liability. So what do you
do?
So maybe to stipulate that you're an
אבא, aba, so meaning to do it maybe to try to trick
the guy so he's not, meaning no one's going to agree to
lend me something if I'll have no liability, so I want to
trick him into having let me have no liability. liability? So what
do you say?
Just have him work for you at the time.
That's what רבא Rava says. נימא ליה אשקיין מיא. neimei lei ashkayan
maya. He'll say, go get me a glass of water. Okay, so
in that sense at the moment where you borrowed the object, he's
quote unquote working for you by bringing you a glass of water.
דהוה שאילה בבעליו de'hava she'ila biv'alav and that would be borrowing with
the owner being under your hire. אי פיקח הוא i pikeiach hu
and if the lender is smart enough to catch on to this
to this scheme, what he'll say, נימא ליה שקייה בדישא והדר אשקיין.
neimei lei shtayei bidisha vehadar ashkayan. So
he'll say I'll lend it to you now for the threshing and
then afterward I'm going to go get you the glass of water.
Like first finish one job and then I'll in order to avoid
that loophole. Yes.
Can employment be can there be a case of employment where somebody
isn't recompensed?
In what sense?
Like when you have to say I'll pay you for this.
Right meaning the hiring could be a נשאל לו nish'al lo he
was lent out to work for him. It doesn't have to be
paid work. It could be any kind of work. It could even
be unpaid work. It's hard to translate. The English has a hard
time translating hiring someone to do a job without paying them because
so much of how we think about doing a job for someone,
you think about doing someone someone a favor something like that is
also an unpaid work. An internship. An internship right. Okay דאמר רבא
de'amar Rava so now another fascinating case to explore how חז"ל Chazal
understood the economics of their time. דאמר רבא de'amar Rava what does
רבא Rava say? דקרי דרדקי dekari dardekei someone who reads so for
the for the kids. The teacher, school teacher, or שתלא shatla is
some kind of a gardener or טבחא tavcha a butcher, a slaughterer,
or אומנא umana
and אומנא umana is
generally a blood letter, right. ספר sapar or a haircutter, a hairdresser.
אמתא כולהו בעידן עבידתייהו כשאילה בבעליו דמו. amata kuleihu be'idan avdeihu keshe'ila
biv'alav damu. So if anyone of these people is working for meaning
if you borrow something from any of these people, that's like שאילה
בבעליו. she'ila biv'alav. Why? Because they're hired sort of for the public
good. They work in a service industry in a way that they're
working for many different people.
And so this is actually מחלוקת ראשונים Machlokes Rishonim how to understand
this. Does this mean when your kid is in school, then the
school teacher is like working for you? Or does it actually mean
that everyone is considered to have hired the school teacher? And that
becomes the question of how do we think of civil servants and
how do we think of public schooling?
Meaning even though my kid may go to a different school since
my taxes are paying for those.
Right, sort of since this person is employed in a for the
public good, even the butcher, the butcher is slaughtering the cows and
chopping up the meat, you go buy the meat, but still the
whole work involved is a public service in that sense. In the
same way or a gardener. The gardener takes care of the medians
in the roads, the gardener takes care of my garden and your
garden and everyone's garden.
So is it because each one of us has employed this person
to work or is it actually because it's on sort of the
public the public dime?
From my understanding something though I mean I really understand the school
teacher, you know, because I mean or maybe not. I don't know.
In other words there's private school, right?
Well back then there was basically only I mean in
חז"ל's Chazal imagination.
But I'm trying to conceptualize this in a modern sense, right?
In other words but I'm trying to understand like the butcher like
it really wasn't just a for profit enterprise?
It was, but the sense that right. So that's why רש"י's Rashi
explanation seems better which is that when you have hired out the
butcher to slaughter a cow and chop up the meat and everything,
I guess that's sort of the question which is that the butcher
does a lot of preparation work in advance of when you actually
buy a steak, right? The butcher has to slaughter the animal and
take and do the ניקור nikur and do the מליחה melichah and
all of the steps of processing the meat until that point he
was still quote unquote working for you the whole week even though
you were only in a business deal with him for five minutes.
So that's sort of the question of how do you think about
the business venture of being a butcher. Is it about just selling
the meat? But it's really much more about the processing and when
you finally pay for the finished product, you're really have also hired
him to work on contract to get it to that point as
well.
But it wouldn't be like let's say you you know there's three
butchers and you never go to that butcher because you don't like
the quality of meat and then he's.
Well that's the מחלוקת Machlokes between רש"י Rashi and the רי"ף. Rif.
Which is that do we consider it as if the community has
hired this person or is it when you're going to that one,
that person is considered to be. The רי"ף Rif says a much
more communal kind of enterprise.
Since he's paid by taxes of the collect. Okay, the butcher. The
רי"ף Rif says all of those.
Well again the חז"ל Chazal sense of having a kosher butcher in
town is kind of you know we don't have they weren't capitalists
in the way that we are. You know the community needs someone
to provide kosher food so that's a communal need in a broader
sense. Okay, the next case. So now we just said a school
teacher
so this would be like the internet guy.
Something like that.
So a school teacher we saw is one example of this. That
is, if the students are coming to the school teacher, the school
teacher is considered to be working for every family in town, and
therefore if you borrow anything, if the school teacher—sorry, if you borrow
anything from the school teacher, well then it's like בעליו עמו ba'alav
imo and then there's no liability. So it's a pretty, pretty good
deal for everybody who's not a school teacher. It's pretty rough on
the school teacher. So the students asked, so אמרו ליה רבנן לרבא.
amru lei rabanan l'Rava. So the students ask Rava, שיילן מר אקפיד.
shaylan mar akpid. So
like what if we borrow something from you,
that is they're trying to claim to Rava that they've hired him
to teach them. And he's saying like if we borrow something from
you, then you're going to lose out basically. So אמר להו, amar
lehu, לאפקועי ממונאי קא בעיתו? l'afku'ei mamonai ka ba'itu?
So are you trying to take my money? That is Rava as
if saying are you hiring me to be the school teacher? So
אדרבא, aderaba, אתון שאלתון לי. atun she'iltun li.
You are hired out to me. That is the students are in
service of the teacher. Now I'm going to have to see why.
So he's going to explain, דאילו אנא מצי לאשתמוטי לכו ממסכתא למסכתא,
d'ilu ana matzi l'ishtamuti l'chu m'masechta l'masechta, אתון לא מציתו לאשתמוטי. atun
lo matzitu l'ishtamuti. Okay.
So Rava says if I want to switch—fast question really quick. Right.
He can choose which מסכתא masechta to be teaching. The teacher gets
to choose what to teach. And therefore, that proves that the teacher
is in charge and not the students. It's not that the students
have hired the teacher to teach them, the teacher has hired out
the students to learn from him. Okay. But now we're going to
see there's a bit of an אוקימתא, okimta, ולא היא. v'lo hi.
Is that really true? איהו שייל להו ביומי דכלה, ihu shayil lehu
b'yomei d'challa, אינהו שאילו ליה בשאר יומי. inhu sha'ilu lei b'sha'ar yomei.
No, there's a difference between יומי דכלה, yomei d'challa, the days before
ניסן Nisan and תשרי. Tishrei. They would have a special כלה, challa,
special gatherings where they would teach specific topics, usually specific to the
holiday, but later it became to teach certain מסכתות. masechtot. But it
became a fixed curriculum, and there was a fixed topic you couldn't
deviate from that. So that in that case the students have obligated
themselves to the teacher to learn whatever the teacher is teaching. But
in the case where on regular days where the teacher gets to
pick, then the teacher is in charge. Interesting how do we think
about the דף יומי Daf Yomi if we have a fixed curriculum
coming from someone else? It certainly sounds like the students have hired
the teacher to teach them. Okay. But I have another question.
I mean, I'm trying to understand this a little bit better, like
again, really trying to apply this to modern times. Like let's say
a school teacher was over the summer.
Right. So that's another question is how to פסקן pasken all these
things. Is he on a yearly salary or is it—you have to
go into שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and everything and see how it
plays out. Some of those questions are really fascinating in terms of
how they probe. How do we think about someone with a salary?
Someone with a 10 months kind of a salary and two months
off, or is it 12 months salary and they're meant to be
preparing. Right. How do you think about a בעל קורא Ba'al Koreh
who gets paid for his preparation during the week and reads on
שבת, Shabbat, things like that. All other sorts of cases. You know,
there's a lot written about all these kind of things.
שו"ת, Shut, a lot of שו"ת Shut
in the public servant.
A בעל קורא Ba'al Koreh certainly is some kind of a public
servant as well. He's hired by the שול shul fund, you know.
So anyway, that's the same kind of—all of these kind of questions
get you into the question of then, okay, so if I borrow
something from this person, are they—is there going to be liability or
not?
If I let's say borrow
from the rabbi's house, right, or whoever
it is, you know,
the שול shul rabbi, the שול shul rabbi, I'm always—you always
win. בעליו עמו, ba'alav imo, he's always working for you. Yeah, it's
a good question.
Send a letter to a פוסק, posek, it's a good question.
You know, obviously some of these questions get us into if there
are explicit rules made, you know, if you make a condition or
if there's מנהג minhag in the שוק shuk or whatever, then a
lot of this can fall away even about דאורייתא De'oraita ממונות mamonot
cases, many of them can be sort of waived because we say
כל תנאי שבממון קיים kol tnai she'b'mamon kayam generally. People can make
specific agreements different from what the תורה Torah requires. Though if you
don't, right, הסתם, hastam, the default should certainly be, you know, it's
a good question. If you borrow something from the rabbi, you're going
to get yourself into a—it's going to be a problematic thing. See,
this is why we learn בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. Okay.
Exactly, no, it's a good question. Okay. So we have one more
case before the משנה. Mishna. So מר בר רב חנינא Mar bar
Rav Chanina אוגר כודנייתא בי חוזאי. ogar kudnyata bei Chozai.
So they were unloading the donkey or they were loading the donkey
in בי חוזאי. bei Chozai. So נפק גדודאי, nafak gaduda'ei, the owner
comes out to adjust אטעונה בהדייהו. atauna bahadeihu. He comes out to
adjust the packages on the donkey. Okay. פשעו בה ומיתה, pash'u bah
v'mita, and somebody messed something up, the—one of the loaders did something
wrong with the donkey and it died. So אתו לקמיה דרבה, atu
l'kamei d'Rabba, they came before רבה. Rabba. חייבינהו, chayivinhu, he said they're
חייב. chayav. But that's strange because it was פשיעה בבעלים, pshia b'ba'alim,
right? So אמרו ליה רבנן לרבא, פשיעה בבעלים היא. amru lei rabanan
le'Rava pshia be'ba'alim hee. So פשעו ביה. poshu bei. So and somebody
messed something up, the one of the loaders did something wrong with
the donkey and it died. So אתו לקמיה דרבה. atu lekamei de'Rava.
So they came before Rava. חייביה. chayveih. They said he's חייב. chayav.
But that's strange because it was פשיעה בבעלים, pshia be'ba'alim, right? So
אמרו ליה רבנן לרבא amru lei rabanan l'Rava, פשיעה בבעלים היא. pshia
b'ba'alim hi. So okay, איכסיף לסוף איגלאי מילתא, ichsif lesof iglai milta,
but in the end it turned out they investigated and it turned
out דלמיסר טעונא היא דנפק, delmeisar tauna hee denafak,
but he only went out not to actually help them with the
loading, but only to watch them do the loading. So if he
wasn't actually working, then it's not really פשיעה בבעלים. pshia be'ba'alim. And
that's part of why some of these cases you have to have
really good witnesses and really good proof to try to verify the
details because it could be a major major you know how much
does a donkey cost in this case, right? One guy loading a
package onto a donkey makes a mistake,
a negligent kind of a mistake, but a mistake nonetheless, and you
have to have real proof whether the owner was there just to
watch or was actually helping. So okay, הניחא למאן דאמר פשיעה בבעלים
פטור. hani'cha leman de'amar pshia be'ba'alim patur. So that makes sense according
to the one who says פשיעה בבעלים pshia be'ba'alim you should be
פטור, patur, משום הכי איכסיף. mishum hachi ichsif. אלא למאן דאמר חייב
אמאי איכסיף? ela leman de'amar chayav amai ichsif? So but if you
say חייב chayav now who says פשיעה בבעלים pshia be'ba'alim is חייב?
chayav? So we'll have to see. So לא פשיעה פשיטו בה lo
pshia pshitu bah
אלא איגנבו ומתה. ela ignavo u'meita. No, so maybe the case was
different. It wasn't a פשיעה pshia case, it was actually a case
where it was stolen. What if the package was stolen or the
donkey was stolen I guess? If the donkey was stolen ומתה v'meita
and then it died כדרכה בגנב k'darkah be'ganav
when the thief was trying to lead the animal, the animal died.
So כדרכה בגנב הוי. k'darkah be'ganav havai. ואתו לקמיה דרבה v'atu lekamei
de'Rava and they came before Rava וחייבינהו v'chayveinhu and he said they're
חייב. chayav. אמרו ליה רבנן לרבא amru lei rabanan le'Rava and the
rabbis said to Rava גניבה בבעלים היא gneiva be'ba'alim hee and that's
a theft case with the owner still there. איכסיף לסוף איגלאי מילתא
דלמיסר טעונא הוא דנפק
ichsif lesof iglai milta
delmeisar tauna hu denafak and the reason why he said חייב chayav
is because the owner wasn't actually there to help with the working,
he was just there to help with the loading. But they switched
it not from a case of פשיעה בבעלים pshia be'ba'alim to a
case of גניבה בבעלים. gneiva be'ba'alim. What do we say? I think
we still say פשיעה בבעלים pshia be'ba'alim you're פטור patur as well.
But the point was that at least there was a מחלוקת machloket
about it earlier, right? About whether we learn from שומר חינם shomer
chinam or not. That was on צדי-ה עמוד ב tzadi-heh amud bet
I think. I'm not remembering exactly.
Yeah, the owner was not helping, he was
supervising but
not help load the animal. Right, but that conceptualizes not helping
because he's not helping with the work, right? But that's so...
Well, but a supervisor is not...
Exactly, that's another... Well, maybe it was a more very casual kind
of supervision. Otherwise I mean if he was really you know there
investigating it, but he certainly wasn't schlapping along. I guess that's sort
of the... Yeah, רש"י Rashi says למיסר לראות שלא ירבו במשאו. lemeisar
lirot shelo yarbu be'masao.
To not to put too much.
That sounds like a real supervisor, isn't just watching, right?
When we say a supervisor is part of the action of the...
Right.
He's part of a team effort, maybe he's the supervisor and then
there are the guys doing the lifting.
Right. Now they retracted... they got embarrassed, they retracted their claim to
Rava because he told them this other detail about the case.
Like literally they turned pale.
They turned right, they turned silver.
They turned silver.
Right. But silver means black usually so
they... they
blushed. They got embarrassed.
Because silver blackens if you...
Right. Right. הכסף העליון כתחתון, hakesef ha'elyon k'tachton, right? Like in פסחים.
Psachim.
They became tarnished. Their face tarnished.
Okay, right. Okay.
So you think we פוסק pasken פשיעה בבעלים pshia be'ba'alim you're פטור?
patur?
I think we say פשיעה בבעלים pshia be'ba'alim you're פטור patur because
we learn it from שומר חינם. shomer chinam. But it was a
מחלוקת. machloket. I think it was... the problem is דף היומי Daf
Yomi goes so fast you forget when things you do two days
ago. I thought on צדי-ה עמוד ב...
tzadi-heh amud bet... what?
Two days ago was pretty good. That's the problem. Okay. We'll continue
with the next משנה. mishna. השואל את הפרה. hashoel et hapara.
Okay. So a case where someone was borrowing a cow, the same
as the previous משנה, mishna, but some more details. השואל את הפרה
שאלה חצי יום ושכרה חצי יום. hashoel et hapara sha'ala chatzi yom
u'schara chatzi yom.
What if you borrowed the cow for half a day and then
rented it for half a day? שאלה היום ושכרה למחר sha'ala hayom
u'schara l'machar or you borrowed it for today and you rented it
for tomorrow. שכרה אחת ושאלה אחת schara achat u'sha'ala achat or you
borrowed one and rented one...
or rented one and borrowed one, sorry. ומתה u'meita and the animal
died. המשאיל אומר hamash'il omer the lender or the renter is going
to say שאולה מתה ביום שהיתה שאולה מתה she'ula meita be'yom she'hayata
she'ula meita of course,
right, because he wants it to be in the case of שאולה
she'ula so there's a high level of liability. שמתה she'meita that if
it died as long as it wasn't מתה מחמת מלאכה meita machamat
melacha the liability is going to be on the שואל. shoel. Okay.
שהיתה שאולה מתה בשעה שהיתה שאולה מתה she'hayata she'ula meita be'sha'a she'hayata
she'ula meita or that at the time when it was borrowed it
died.
והלה אומר איני יודע ve'hala omer eini yodeia and
the borrower says I don't know.
Now he should definitely say I know the other way. You'd always
do that.
Well, but he's telling the truth but
the other guy probably doesn't know either.
Okay, so okay. Somebody was watching something, somebody was watching something else,
it's to illustrate
the... Okay, the guy who borrowed the cow says איני יודע. eini
yodeya. So חייב, chayav, he's liable to pay. Now we're going to
see as רש"י Rashi on the גמרא Gemara points out this is
a case comes up many different times ברי ושמא ברי עדיף. bari
veshema bari adif. That is, if someone makes a sure claim, it
was borrowed at the time that it died, and then someone makes
an unsure claim, I don't know, we say the ברי עדיף, bari
adif, the sure claim wins out against an unsure claim. However, there
are many exceptions to that and generally in this kind of a
case we're going to see there should be many other avenues that
could develop. The main question here is going to be well, first
of all,
let's finish the משנה Mishnah first and we'll see. Okay. השוכר אומר
שכורה מתה ביום שהיתה שכורה hasocher omer sechura metah beyom shehayta sechura
and the one who rented out the animal, the other one, right,
said, no, it died at the time that it was rented. מתה
בשעה שהיתה שכורה. metah besha'ah shehayta sechura.
No, שכורה מתה ביום שהיתה שכורה.
sechura metah
beyom shehayta sechura. So השוכר אומר, hasocher omer, right, the one who
rented it, right, says, it's interesting that it flipped, right, he's focused
on the rental because the renter has a lower level liability. השוכר
אומר שכורה מתה ביום שהיתה שכורה מתה בשעה שהיתה שכורה. hasocher omer
sechura metah beyom shehayta sechura metah besha'ah shehayta sechura. So he says
it was while it was rented that it died, so he'll have
a lower liability, he won't have to pay for it. והלה אומר
איני יודע vehalah omer eini yodeya and the owner says I don't
know. So now again we'll say ברי ושמא ברי עדיף, bari veshema
bari adif, פטור. patur. So that's why he's exempt in this case.
Would that also be kind of obvious from the flips when you
have both cases? Okay. What if he didn't, what if he said
I don't know?
If they made a claim, they would make a claim. Then we
would have a different kind of a case. We'd have two competing
claims and we're going to have
to then proof and
witnesses or both ברי.
bari. Right, if both of them have a שמא ושמא shema veshema
it gets tricky because nobody really has a real claim. But ברי
וברי bari vebari cases, that's like what we had the first דף,
daf, right, שנים אוחזין shnayim ochazin case, right? And I mean we
have so many different ways to resolve
conflicting cases. So let's take a look. The last case is going
to clarify.
It's like a contract, right?
It's a determined, it was a handshake contract.
Which day was the rented day and which day was the borrowed?
Well, they don't have a שטר, shtar, right? It's all word of
mouth. That's the problem.
It could become pretty difficult.
Maybe
I'm borrowing it, or I'm taking it for two days, I'll pay
you for one and not the other, and they didn't specify
how you would split it.
Right, that's part of what's problem. So the last line of the
משנה Mishnah just to say: זה אומר שאולה וזה אומר שכורה, zeh
omer sheulah vezeh omer sechura, right? So when they actually contradict each
other, they both make a solid claim, ברי וברי bari vebari kind
of a case, ישבע השוכר ששכורה מתה. yishava hasocher shesechura metah. So
the renter, the one who sort of doesn't have the claim, the
stronger angle of claim because it's not his animal to begin with,
so he has to take an oath that it was rented at
the time it died. זה אומר איני יודע וזה אומר איני יודע
יחלוקו. zeh omer eini yodeya vezeh omer eini yodeya yachloku. If they
neither of them knows then it's שמא ושמא, shema veshema, neither of
them knows what happened, then they just split it.
Now meaning in the case we split
the liability, right?
Meaning in the case we just had, like let's say, yeah, okay
I'm going to borrow for two days, one of them will be,
you know, if I didn't specify which day, then that'd be a
יחלוקו. yachloku. Because you can't be ברי bari on that.
Because I don't know which day,
I can't be ברי bari on that either. That has to be
יחלוקו. yachloku.
Right. Unless, yeah I guess so. So that sounds like it gets
you into a, so and יחלוקו, yachloku, what does it mean? Basically
means you're going to have to pay me half, right? You split
the liability, so you'd have to pay half. What's interesting about this
case is what oath is this? What do you mean? The שוכר
socher takes an oath that it was ששכורה מתה, shesechura metah, when
it was rented it died. What oath is that? That's not a
שבועת השומרים. shvuat hashomrim.
That's something different. Yeah, so that's very strange.
So what was said again?
The oath that the שוכר socher takes
when he says it's the hired one versus the borrowed one.
Right. In the third case in the משנה, Mishnah, right? זה אומר
שאולה וזה אומר שכורה ישבע השוכר ששכורה מתה. zeh omer sheulah vezeh
omer sechura yishava hasocher shesechura metah. The renter has to take an
oath that it was the, it died while he was renting it
and not while he was borrowing it.
And some people call it something called שבועת השוכרים. shvuat hasocherim.
We don't have such a, no, because it's also different than the
whole point of שבועת השומרים shvuat hashomrim is to provide an exemption
to say, I'm not liable at all, right? Which is sort of
what he's trying to do here, right? He is a שוכר socher
and he's trying to say it was such a high level of
אונס ones that I'm not liable even if I'm a שוכר. socher.
But still it's different than the שבועת השומרים. shvuat hashomrim. And תוספות
Tosafot is big discussion.
But this is an oath on a fact.
Right, it's about a fact, it's swearing about a fact, which is
like the oath we had in the beginning of בבא מציעא, Bava
Metzia, which if you remember is not one of the שבועות דאורייתא.
shvuot deoraita. The way it comes up on ג עמוד א, gimel
amud aleph, the final conclusion of the
סוגיא, sugia, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says שבועה זו תקנת חכמים היא
שלא יהא כל אחד ואחד הולך ותוקף בטליתו של חבירו.
shvua zo takanat chachamim hi shelo yehei kol
echad ve-echad holech vetokeif betalito shel chaveiro. It reminds me very much
about this שבועה. shvua. This שבועה shvua is it's זה אומר zeh
omer this, זה אומר zeh omer this, זה ישבע שבשעה ששכורה מתה,
zeh yishava shebesha'ah shesechura metah, right? You could almost imagine...
How would he know that?
The guy because he made a claim. But he says he knows
for sure.
I don't know.
So that's part of what's complicated about this סוגיא sugya and that's
why there's so many תוספות Tosfos about it is trying to get
into the details of how does this שבועה shvua work and we're
going to see some of the mechanism here is תוספות's Tosfos suggestion
is that actually and actually the גמרא Gemara suggestion is that there
was some other שבועה shvua hanging over them before they even got
into this agreement and it's really more like a גלגול שבועה gilgul
shvua kind of case. This taking this שבועה shvua is only because
you were already obligated to take some other שבועה shvua and now
this one kicks in as well.
Well that's according to תוספות Tosfos on the previous עמוד. amud.
That's basically what the גמרא Gemara says.
דהוה ליה שאולה מתה? de-hava leh she'ula meta? No, שבועה על ידי
גלגול. shvua al yedei gilgul.
Right. So that and that's based on what the גמרא Gemara says.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara
says yeah.
Isn't that according to that דעה deah that says every שומר shomer
has to swear anyway? לא פשעתי בה? lo pashati bah?
But even here right because the שומר shomer doesn't have to swear
unless it doesn't fit the regular שבועת השומרים. shvuat hashomrim. That's sort
of the point. That's תוספות's Tosfos point.
No like when is it according to I forget which דעה deah
it was every שומר shomer always has to swear שלא פשעתי בה,
shelo pashati bah, שלא שלחתי יד shelo shalachti yad and שלא זה.
shelo zeh. Remember that was that דעה?
deah? Right if there's some kind of a case. What even if
he's not trying to exempt himself?
Well no obviously not no but I'm saying that like you know
but there's
a whole bunch of things not just...
yeah it's a three part שבועה, shvua, שבועה שלא פשעתי בה, shvua
shelo pashati bah, שבועה שלא שלחתי בה יד shvua shelo shalachti bah
yad and I forget the third one.
Yeah I forget what the third שבועה shvua is. שאינה ברשותי. she-eina
birshuti. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה. shma mina. So
we learn from this משנה Mishna seemingly something very strange. מנה לי
בידך והלה אומר איני יודע. maneh li beyadcha vehalah omer eini yodea.
If someone says Mike you owe me a hundred dollars and Michael
says I don't know, חייב chayav
right? What happened? ברי ושמא ברי עדיף bari veshema bari adif right?
So if you go up to somebody and say you know you
owe me a hundred dollars or I lent you a hundred dollars
and it's time to pay me back and he says I don't
know, so you're חייב chayav to pay.
Well I don't know if you could say that I mean because
you know there's a question of whether there was a transaction at
all. In this case we know there's a transaction the question is
just... do we?
The guy could say it was my cow and the cow died.
No but meaning I know that I borrowed a cow and you
know that you lent me a cow. The question is just okay
whose part of the city it is.
Well let's say it differently. I lent
you a hundred dollars you agree that at some point you lent
me a hundred dollars and you don't remember whether you paid me
back or not.
Okay that's I'm familiar with that. No okay so you just come
to
me and you know...
I have no idea I have no idea if I ever borrowed
money from you.
Right. Okay so לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב נחמן? leima tehei tiyuvta d'Rav
Nachman? Maybe this משנה Mishna is a תיובתא tiyuvta contradicts רב נחמן's
Rav Nachman position? דאיתמר de'itmar what did רב נחמן Rav Nachman say?
מנה לי בידך והלה אומר איני יודע. maneh li beyadcha vehalah omer
eini yodea. רב הונא ורב יהודה אמרי חייב. Rav Huna ve-Rav Yehuda
amri chayav. רב נחמן ורבי יוחנן אמרי פטור. Rav Nachman ve-Rabbi Yochanan
amri patur. So it's מחלוקת אמוראים machloket Amoraim whether in such a
case you're you have to pay or you don't have to pay.
כדאמר רב נחמן k'de'amar Rav Nachman so and רב נחמן's Rav Nachman
opinion is like what רב נחמן Rav Nachman said כגון שיש עסק
שבועה ביניהם. kegon sheyesh esek shvua beineihem.
No so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said the reason that in such
a case where you would be חייב chayav would be if there
was a שבועה shvua between you and then you could take the
שבועה. shvua. But if you were פטור patur the reason you're פטור
patur is because there was no שבועה. shvua. הכא נמי כגון שיש
עסק שבועה ביניהם. hacha nami kegon sheyesh esek shvua beineihem. So too
we should say רב נחמן Rav Nachman would respond to our משנה
Mishna the reason you're חייב chayav in this משנה Mishna and the
reason why
the the שוכר socher would
have to pay
is because he was liable for some other שבועה. shvua. But what?
But if it's ברי ושמא bari veshema his own claim is a
שמא shema claim so he can't take a שבועה shvua and that's
why he's חייב. chayav. So what does it get you into? It
gets you into okay so two steps. He's חייב chayav to take
a שבועה shvua for something else.
Some unrelated some unrelated case
with the same משאיל mash'il with the same משאיל. mash'il. Then we
say the שבועה shvua kicks in in this case because of גלגול
שבועה. gilgul shvua. And then
second step since he can't take a שבועה shvua about it because
his claim is a שמא shema claim it's only a doubtful claim
then he has to pay. That's מתוך שאינו יכול להשבע ישלם. mitoch
she'eino yachol lehishava yeshalem. Because he can't swear he has to pay.
It's a שמא shema case.
Right ברי ושמא. bari veshema. Right.
Then right.
So it's not actually saying ברי ושמא bari veshema wins but
there's a גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua and it's ברי ושמא. bari veshema.
It's as if he's refusing to take the שבועה. shvua.
Right because a גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua you can't take the שבועה.
shvua. And there's a whole discussion in מסכת שבועות Masechet Shvuos in
the fourth פרק perek that gets into this quite a bit about
all the cases of גלגול שבועה gilgul shvua and this one you
know monetary liabilities that then get you into one שבועה shvua and
then you have to take you know many many other שבועות shvuot
that you would not not normally be obligated to take. גלגול שבועה
gilgul shvua you can be forced to take a שבועה shvua for
all sorts of cases even cases that normally don't have the liability
of a שבועה. shvua.
But the point
is...
Presumably we always פסקן pasken like
רב נחמן Rav Nachman in ממונות. mamonot. All right. Okay.
So כשיש עסק שבועה ביניהם. kesheyesh esek shvua beneihem. So היכי דמי
heichi dami עסק שבועה? esek shvua? כי דרבה דאמר רבה מנה לי
בידך והלה אומר אין לך בידי אלא חמישים. kiderabba de'amar Rabba mane
li beyadecha vehallaz omer ein lecha beyadi ella chamishim. Okay, so it's
like a מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzat case. So he said you owe
me $100 and then he says no no no I only owe
you $50. והשאר איני יודע. vehash'ar eini yodea. The other 50 is
not I don't owe you the other 50 but it's I don't
know whether I owe you 50. So that's that's a מודה במקצת
modeh b'miktzat שמא shema kind of a case. מתוך שאינו יכול להישבע
משלם. mitoch she'eino yachol lishava meshallem. And that's a kind of a
parallel case where again you forced yourself into take a שבועה shvua
because of מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. But since you made the מודה
במקצת modeh b'miktzat claim as a שמא shema claim then you can't
actually take the שבועה shvua and then you've blocked yourself out.
Let's stop there with the גמרא. Gemara.
There's not much else I'd like to say about this סוגיא sugya
just yet. Tell me about פשיעה בבעלים p'shia
b'be'alim whether it's at the end do they have time now?
פשיעה בבעלים p'shia b'be'alim is פטור patur or חייב? chayav? Let's take
a look. I think we've done a צדי ה עמוד ב. Tzadi
Heh amud bet. You could go look at a רמב"ם. Rambam. You
could go look at a רמב"ם Rambam too. It's a good place
go look at the beginning of
שאילה ופקדון. She'ila u'Pikadon. שאילה ופקדון She'ila u'Pikadon should be towards the
beginning.